<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honorable Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London at Guild-Hall Chappel, on January 30th, 1677/78 by Henry Hesketh.</title>
            <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1615</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R10690</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11821209</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11821209</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 496:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honorable Lord Mayor and aldermen of the city of London at Guild-Hall Chappel, on January 30th, 1677/78 by Henry Hesketh.</title>
                  <author>Hesketh, Henry, 1637?-1710.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Will. Leach ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, I, 17-18 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:49568:1"/>
            <opener>
               <signed>Chaplyn Major.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Jovis XXXImo.</hi> 
                     <hi>die Janarii</hi> 1677. <hi>Anno<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> Carol. Secundi Angliae,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>XXXmo</hi>s.</date>
               </dateline>
            </opener>
            <p>This Court doth deſire Mr. <hi>Hesketh</hi> to Print his Sermon, preached yeſterday at the <hi>Guild-hall</hi> Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, before the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of this City.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Wagſtaffe.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49568:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Right Honorable Lord Mayor AND ALDERMEN OF THE CITY of LONDON AT Guild-Hall Chappel, ON JANUARY 30th 1677/8;</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Hesketh</hi> Rector of <hi>Charlewood</hi> in <hi>Surrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Will. Leach,</hi> at the <hi>Crown</hi> in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> near the <hi>Royal Exchange.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49568:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Guil. Jane,</hi> R. P. D. <hi>Hen.</hi> Epiſ. <hi>Lond.</hi> a Sacris Dom.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>Feb. 2. 1677.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49568:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 SAM. 1.17, 18.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And David lamented with this lamentation o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over Saul, and over Jonathan his ſon.</p>
                  <p>Alſo he bad them teach the children of Judah the uſe of the bow: behold, it is written in the book of Jaſher.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>AMong all Nations in the World, that have been bleſſed with any ſober ſenſe of things; we ſhall find this ever to have been a fixed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Cuſtom, to ſignalize times of extraordinary Occurrences with ſome ſpecial Marks and Characters, which might commend them to more than common obſervation, judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it very becoming and proper, that ſuch Times ſhould not paſs only in the comnon crowd, but that as the Accidents of them were extraregular, ſo mens entertainments thereof ſhould be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, Seaſons of great ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and ſignal diſaſters, have been ſpent in, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards remembred by deep and afflictive reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49568:3"/> and theſe men have called Faſts, and marked them in their Calendars for Times of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Mourning.</p>
            <p>This is a Cuſtom, which as it may ſerve to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny excellent ends of Prudence, and advance ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny great Purpoſes of publick Good; ſo it ſeems to carry a good tincture of Religion upon it, and to derive a ſufficient warranty from it.</p>
            <p>For ſince it ought to be the care, as well as it is much the duty of all good men, that have a due veneration of God, and any becoming ſenſe of a Divine Providence ſuperintending the World, and all the affairs of men in it, to permit the paſſages of no day to paſs unobſerved, it will much more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come matter of their care, not to ſuffer extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and ſignal Diſpoſes of Providence to do ſo: Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſince God intends all theſe things as Leſſons and Inſtructions to the World, to awaken men to due thoughts of Himſelf, and more concerning regards to their own Duty.</p>
            <p>It is therefore laid down in holy Scripture as a ſure character of an evil man, to be regardleſs and unobſervant of Gods common judgements, but it is a rank ſign of Irreligion, and next to an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſtical contempt of God, not to be deeply af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected, when his hand is lifted up in greater chaſtiſements, and not to entertain a very humble ſenſe of his ſeverer Inflictions.</p>
            <p>It is the juſt Honour of this day, that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49568:3"/> its Inſtitution is founded upon all theſe great Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Prudence and Religion, and warranted by Precedents among all ſober Nations of Prudence, to impreſs (by the obſervation of it) upon men the deeper ſenſe of the ſad accidents thereof, and of Religion, in entertaining ſuch great afflictions with thoſe humiliations and tears, which both they, and the ſins of this Nation, that occaſion'd them, do moſt juſtly call for.—And it will be no preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice nor diſparagement to it, to obſerve, that it ſtands warranted by precedent, and may plead its vindication from the ſuitable practice of the beſt and wiſeſt, and moſt religious perſons in all Ages of the World, and particularly of one no leſs eminent for all theſe, then <hi>David,</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet as well as King, who upon the ſad news ef the tragical death of <hi>Saul,</hi> effected by the Arms of the Philiſtins, upon thoſe unhappy plains of <hi>Gilboa,</hi> lamented over him, with this lamentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on following, <hi>Alſo he bad them teach the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Judah the uſe of the bow: behold it is written in the book of Jaſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words I take notice of theſe three principal Obſervables.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>David</hi>'s inſtituting a Form of Lamentation for the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael. And Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid lamented with this lamentation over Saul, and over Jonathan his ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His enjoyning the people to be taught to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49568:4"/> joyn with him in it. <hi>Alſo he bad them teach the children of Judah the uſe of the bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. His recording of it for the Notice and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſucceſſive Generations. <hi>Behold it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the book of Jaſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of all which three obſervables (I ſhall beg pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience) while I ſpeak ſomething.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In their more independent and abſolute ſenſe, or at leaſt only as they relate to their own matter, and are a Hiſtory to us of what is paſt and gone.</p>
            <p n="2">2. In their relative ſenſe, and as they have an aſpect upon us, and the buſineſs of this day; in which ſenſe we may call this, the Application of the matter of them to our ſelves.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I begin with them in the firſt ſenſe, and therein with</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt obſervable in them, <hi>David</hi> Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuting a Form of Lamentation for the death of <hi>Saul. And David lamented with this lamentation over Saul, and over Jonathan his ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to which I do not deſire to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted with the clamorous objection of this age, againſt all publick Forms in any thing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative to Divine Service.</p>
            <p>It is very well, and a happy thing, that the great ſtarters of the diſpute have ſufficiently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed their own Maximes: and the impoſing a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Directory, will make ridiculous all general Arguments againſt Liturgy.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49568:4"/>
            <p>It is ſufficient; that the Inſtitution of this ſtands warranted by, and may claim a right in all thoſe great Reaſons for a ſtanding Liturgy, which yet do, and I am confident will ſtand unaſſoil'd, to the great diſſolution. And if there be any man that thinks otherwiſe, he hath now a fair oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to ſignalize himſelf, and gain the reputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a daring <hi>Goliah,</hi> by challenging all the Armies of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and I little doubt, but he ſhall meet with the fate of his great Denominator, and I am the more confirmed herein, becauſe here is a <hi>David</hi> that ſtands ready to take up the Gantlet.</p>
            <p>And it may not perhaps be impertinent or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant to obſerve, that, as if there were ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Magick or Charm in the name of <hi>David,</hi> all that relates to him hath never been controverted; and of all the parts in the Liturgy, the Pſalms, the Metrical compoſures of <hi>David</hi> (which are ſo great a part of it) have leaſt of all been diſputed, and I cannot gueſs at a reaſon of this, unleſs it be that their pretences to the Spirit, would hence have received their own confutation; and all men ſee it was not the Spirit of God that acted them; for there is no doubt but that can indite Metre, as well as harangues in Proſe, but their fears of this, would never permit them yet to put it unto tryal.</p>
            <p>But I paſs all this, and proceed to conſider this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the conſideration of which we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49568:5"/> ſhall meet with a complication of Reaſons, every one of which might juſtly occaſion a lamentation.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For firſt to dye, to leave theſe ſplendid ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitations for a cold grave, to leave dear friends to converſe with putrefaction and rottenneſs, to have theſe beautiful Piles tumbled into confuſion and duſt, to have our vaſt Poſſeſſions and Manors ſhrunk up into a few feet of Earth, a pitchy Sheet, and a ſtrait Coffin, are to moſt men living ſad ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and the thoughts of them rarely entertain'd without ſighs and a tear. Mourning is therefore one attendant always upon Funerals: Amongſt the Jews there was always a ſet of common Mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, that their mourning might be more ſolemn, and their lamentations more affective, and I find it threatned as a judgement to <hi>Jehojakim,</hi> that he ſhould have an inglorious and contemptible Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial, and ſhould have none to make formal lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation for him, <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.18.</p>
            <p>And whoever conſults the Genius of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, will find its compaſſions are as great, its affections as quick, and its ſenſe as ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as before; and all it deſigns in this caſe is not to dam up the Fountain, but take care that it flow only in due meaſures; not that we ſorrow not at all, but that we ſorrow in due proportions, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the meaſures of faith, and with the abatements and intermixtures of Chriſtian hope, for that I take to be the meaning of that limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49568:5"/> in the Apoſtolical Canon, <hi>That ye ſorrow not as the Gentiles, which have no hope,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 4.13.</p>
            <p>But this is but a ſmall matter, and the leaſt of theſe conſiderations; for if death be juſt matter of Lamentation, certainly the death of a King is much more ſo, when the Tall Cedars bow, and the ſtrong Oaks crack, and are made to ſtoop low, and compelled to lie proſtrate upon the breaſt of their common Mother, then as the ſtorm is more ſtrong ſo it is more awakening, and ſummons the moſt ſerious regards and moſt real reſentments.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is alſo in this matter, for when death knocks but at the common door, the Mourners ſtrike but the common key; but when it rifles Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laces, and enters into the Chambers of Kings, and thoſe that are gods die like men, and fall equal Trophies to this rude Conqueror, and are dragged after the wheels of his triumphing Chariot, there you ſhall ſee always the Scene is dreſſed with all the ſolemnities of the deepeſt ſorrow, the croud of Mourners is great, and the Herald's skill is needful to marſhal the troops, and to preſerve order in the great confuſion.</p>
            <p>And this wants not good appearances of reaſon, to plead its juſtification, for as the wiſe Jews ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>David</hi> worth ten thouſand of them, &amp; his life of more value than the lives of thrice ſo many thouſand of common perſons. So indeed have all wiſe &amp; civilized Nations accounted after the ſame
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49568:6"/> rate, and as they have ſolemnized the <hi>Natalitia</hi> of their Kings with all expreſſions of publick joy, ſo they have obſerved the days of their death with as great demonſtrations of Mourning, when Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid in ſolemn manner lamented the death of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> he gave a ſufficient reaſon he thought for it, in ſaying, <hi>Know ye not that there is a Prince and a great man fallen this day in Iſrael;</hi> and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if the fall of a Prince, much more the fall of a King alſo will warrant mourning, and if <hi>David</hi> might juſtly lament the death of <hi>Abner,</hi> he might more juſtly do ſo upon the death of <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this alſo is much ſhort of what yet remains unconſidered; for if the death of Kings be juſt matter of ſorrow, then the more untimely and violent, and preternatural the death is, the more afflictedly ought it ſtill to be reſented.</p>
            <p>When the Taper dies regularly, having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed all its oyl, and exhauſted all its ſtore of moyſture, it expires quietly, and no man is much concerned at it, but when it meets with an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption by the rude careſſes of an impetuous blaſt, then its ſnuff grows offenſive, and all men take notice of it, and are concerned at the diſaſter.</p>
            <p>And ſo it is with Kings in this caſe, when they come into their Sepulchers as ſhocks of corn fully ripened and in their ſeaſon, as <hi>Eliphaz</hi> elegantly, <hi>Job</hi> 5.26. when they die the common death of all men, and go down to the grave in a good old
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49568:6"/> age, having honourably paſſed all the ſtages and periods of humane life, there we pay them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly but a common tribute, and drop a tear up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Hearſe, and bewail them upon the ſtock of common frailty, and our grief that they are gone receives a juſt abatement from the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that God ſpared them to us ſo long; but when theſe fall like untimely fruit ſhaken by an unſeaſonable violent unkind wind; there the chanels are full, the ſtreams run high, the Accents are deep, the Minſtrels ſtrike the dolefulleſt note, and (as it is ſaid of <hi>David</hi> here) men commonly ever exceed in their expreſſions of grief, for ſo when good <hi>Joſiah</hi> fell by the Arms of the <hi>Aſſyri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> at the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> the people lamented the ſad Accident at <hi>Megiddo,</hi> with a ſorrow that for the greatneſs of it became proverbial.</p>
            <p>And yet the greateſt of theſe conſiderations is behind; for if all theſe things happen without any fault or concurrence of ours, then our ſorrow even from thence receives a great extenuation, but if we have any ways been contributive to the miſchief, or been negligent, and failing to do our utmoſt towards preventing of it, then indeed our ſorrow is much more juſt, yea it is neceſſary.</p>
            <p>I put theſe two together in one period and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration you ſee; and truly I do not know well how to part, or diſtinguiſh betwixt them, for though it be certain that there is a difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49568:7"/> them abſolutely conſidered, and he that actually embrues his hands in blood, is more guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty than he that paſſed by, and did not endeavour to reſcue, though even he be greatly guilty alſo.—Yet in this caſe I am now upon, there is little or no difference at all, for Subjects are as equally ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to aſſiſt their Kings in all ſtraits and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, as not to reſiſt, or riſe up againſt them to bring them into the ſame, and their failure in the firſt is as criminal as doing the ſecond, and only differs from it, as the cauſe from the effect, for therefore ſome men are encouraged to attempt the latter, becauſe others are negligent and failing in the former, upon which reaſon it is certain if either exceed in guilt, it is the former.</p>
            <p>I take this occaſion to diſcourſe a little this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, becauſe of a great and a moſt dangerous mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake that I obſerve to be Epidemical and common about it.—For as ſome men boaſt they obey the Law, if they quietly ſubmit to the penalty and pay the forfeiture, as well as he that performs the poſitive duty, for the neglect of which the former penalty is threatned.—So other men are apt to commend their Loyalty as much for not reſiſting, as others do theirs, for protecting their King.</p>
            <p>But as the former of theſe is an Error, than which few are more dangerous as to the honor and power of Laws, or more wholly defeating of the great end of them, which is that their ſanctions
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49568:7"/> may be obeyed, and the things done that they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyn, for which cauſe it is that penalties are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed, not as ends of the Law, but as motives to engage to compliance therewith.—From whence we may take juſt occaſion to detect the ſophiſtry and vanity of that common diſtinction of obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence into active and paſſive, upon the ſtrength of which many men hope to clear themſelves from rebellion and diſobedience.—I have many times wondred at learned mens accepting this diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but not at all at their pains to ſolve theſe mens pretences for themſelves, when they have admitted it; and therefore I think it needful firſt to detect the fallacy of it, and then all the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from it, are their own confutations, and I cannot but think a ſmall matter may ſuffice to do it: for I do not know how ever to truſt my own faculties in judging of any one thing in the world, if paſſive obedience be not a contradiction in the adjunct.—And that both as to the words themſelves, about which plain evidence ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedes all diſpute, and as to the ſubrſtate matter, or thing ſignified by them; for I would gladly be told, whether any man ſuffer for obeying the Law, or violating it? No man can pretend he doth it for the firſt; and to confeſs the latter, and yet pretend obedience, is to pretend that he obeys the Law, when he confeſſeth he violates i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; and I think a contradiction cannot be plainer in any inſtance.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49568:8"/>
            <p>This I take to be certain, the end of the Law is obedience, and the annexing penalties, is but an Art to engage to it, and the ſuffering it conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial only upon tranſgreſſion; and for men to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend that the Law is equally fulfilled when the forfeiture is paid, as when the condition is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, is the ſame thing as to ſay, that he that is broken upon the wheel for Murther or Parricide, obeys the fifth and ſixth Commandments, as well as he that honours his Father, and never did any kind of violence to his Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Beſides it will fix the moſt reproachful cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter upon all Legiſlators whatſoever, and make them little better than ſo many Tyrants or De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, in making Laws which if thoſe under them obey, they are pleaſed, but if they tranſgreſs and ſuffer, they are ſtill as well pleaſed. It was the juſt reproach of <hi>Draco</hi>'s Laws, that they were writ in blood, but this is greater to all Laws, for it makes them to deſign blood. I confeſs it is neceſſary to vindicate the honour of Laws, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict penalties for the breach of them; but I take it, this is not at all the end of them. I have much more to ſay to this ſubject, but that the digreſſion would be too unbecoming.</p>
            <p>Now the truth is, juſt ſuch a miſtake as this is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Subjection to Laws, there is alſo about Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; Subjection to Kings, and it is every jot as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious to the ſafety of Kings, as the other is to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49568:8"/> the honour of Laws; for ſome men are as apt to claim the honour of Loyalty, if they do not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually reſiſt their King, as others are that venture their lives and fortunes to aſſiſt and vindicate them againſt thoſe that do reſiſt them—But how per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicious this is to the ſafety of Kings, and how contrary to the true notion of Loyalty, will ſoon be made appear.</p>
            <p>For if Subjects be only obliged to the firſt, and diſcharge their duty in it, I would fain know how the ſafety of Kings ſhall be aſſured, and who ſhall be obliged to aſſert them againſt violence and Treaſon? All Nations have ever held the Perſons of Kings to be ſacred, and accounted it their duty to protect them from all dangers, and therefore have judged it needful to have Septs and Guards ſtill about them.—But according to this doctrine all this is needleſs; but the Apologue tells us, who they were that would perſwade the Sheep to diſcard their Guard. And it is eaſie to ſee into the deſigns of all ſuch perſwaſions.</p>
            <p>Beſides Loyalty ſure is a nobler thing, and in what breaſt ſoever it breaths, will put a man upon endeavouring when need is, to defend his King, as well as forbearing to do him violence; and <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that conſiders thoſe Oaths that Subjects bind themſelves in to Princes, will clearly ſee that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they are obliged not only not to do violence to them themſelves, but to do all that in them
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49568:9"/> lieth, that others alſo may not do it, and it is trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon when the King ſets up his Standard for his defence, not to repair unto it. And where duty is tied on men by Oaths, there to fail in it, is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly common guilt, but died with perjury.</p>
            <p>And if it were otherwiſe, we ſhould make Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty a pitiful poor ſneaking thing, and give Kings infinitely leſs power over their Subjects, than every petty Maſter hath over his Servants; for thus much every ſuch perſon expects from him that ſerves him, that he ſhould not only not do him wrong himſelf, but to his power endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour that none elſe may; and every man will condemn him for a wicked ſervant, that fails to do thus: and why a Subject in the like caſe is not equally criminal, will be hard to ſhow.</p>
            <p>Thoſe famous Stories in the Annals of all Ages, of Subjects that have interpoſed their own bodies, betwixt danger and their Kings, and received wounds themſelves, that were lighting upon them, and thereby purchaſed to themſelees a little kind of eternity, while the Records of time laſt, are clear Evidences of thus much, that in all thoſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges this hath been counted the Duty of Subjects, and thoſe have been ſignalized for happy, that have had opportunity of doing it.</p>
            <p>Thus <hi>Abiſhai</hi>'s ſuccoring <hi>David</hi> againſt the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of <hi>Iſhbi-Benob</hi> the Giant, is recorded in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture, and all the people congratulate the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49568:9"/> fact, and vow never to permit their King to come again into the like danger, and will rather fight his Battels without his Conduct, than expoſe him to any hazard at all, and you ſhall ſcarcely meet with any conſiderable Hiſtory, wherein there are not many parallel inſtances recorded.</p>
            <p>And whoever ſhall pleaſe to read the ſtory of <hi>Antius Reſtio</hi> his Servant, when his Maſter was proſcribed by the Roman Triumvicate, as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by that excellent Patrician <hi>Valerius Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus,</hi> will be able to make this Obſervation, that great harſhneſs, and unkindneſs in a Maſter, do not diſcharge the Servant from this Duty, for that Servant had receiv'd ſome extraordinary marks of an undeſerved diſpleaſure; and yet for all that, thought it his Duty, when other Servants were contriving for themſelves, to contrive what he could for the ſafety of his Maſter, which he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily effected by a very prudent ſtratagem.</p>
            <p>And therefore it was a pitiful excuſe, that a Gentleman made for his diſloyalty to the late King, by ſeeking to juſtifie his treaſon, becauſe his Majeſty once in haſte ſwitched him, for croſſing his way, as he was riding hard at Hunting. And yet his greateſt Enemies could never pretend any ſuch ſhew of unkindneſs; and I am confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in believing, he never did any man more harm.</p>
            <p>But now according to the Doctrine I am op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49568:10"/> all theſe ſtories ſhould be cancelled, and expunged out of Hiſtory, the Honour of Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph ſhould be denied to thoſe Worthies, and their Merits equalled to theirs, who could un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concernedly behold the danger of their Kings, and ſtand quietly by, with their Arms folded up, and their Hands in their Boſom.</p>
            <p>But it is too great an honour to ſo dull a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to ſtay ſo long in its confutation, any de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of Honour will deteſt and abhor it. And as the Loyalty of thoſe Perſons, who were ſo happily inſtrumental in that Miracle of our preſent King's ſtrange preſervation, will be remembred with Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, and Bleſſing, and Honour, as long as Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty reſts in the Boſom of this Nation: So it will be an evidence to the World, that all true Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhmen abhor ſuch a thin and baſe loyalty, as ſhall think it enough to abſtain only from offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but not to interpoſe at all in defending their King.</p>
            <p>But I return to the matter before us in the Text, and from what hath been ſaid, we may ſafely infer, that if it were thus, <hi>David</hi> might well lament <hi>Sauls</hi> death; that is, if he had ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther been contributive directly to it, or failing in his endeavours to prevent it.</p>
            <p>For all the former conſiderations made this matter but an infelicity; but this renders it a great guilt, and therefore juſtly to be ſorrowed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49568:10"/> for, we may juſtly ſorrow for our miſeries: but when we pull down theſe upon us by our own ſins, we may much more do ſo; we lawfully may lament our infelicities, but we needs muſt lament our ſins.</p>
            <p>Now thus (it is too evident) it was with <hi>David</hi> in this caſe, for firſt he had been actually in arms againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> and though much may be ſaid for it, conſidering ſome circumſtances, yet conſidering the whole matter, we may ſafely pronounce of it, that it was certainly unjuſtifiable, for there were more ſafer ways of avoyding the diſpleaſure and anger of <hi>Saul,</hi> than by raiſing an Army of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laws and vitious perſons, and appearing in actual rebellion againſt him.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially alſo if he uſed thoſe arms directly againſt <hi>Saul,</hi> and that he either did, or at leaſt of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to do, we are aſſured from the proffer and boaſt he made to <hi>Achiſh</hi> thereof, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28.2. and it will fix a deep guilt on the fact, whatever the intention was; for if he promiſed this, and intended not to perform it, he was an hypocrite, and if he did, he was a Traytor and a Rebel.</p>
            <p>But if none of this were true, yet the leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil that can be ſaid, is, that he yielded not that aſſiſtance unto <hi>Saul</hi> which he might have done, and by which poſſibly he might have avert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this ſad fate; for who knows how far the arms of <hi>David</hi> (in this juncture) might have contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49568:11"/> to the overthrow of the Philiſtines? and who knows not but that this might have been a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py means of a firm reconciliation betwixt him and <hi>Saul,</hi> and an occaſion of more endearing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to all the people, and occaſioning the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> once more to ſing his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>And there is little reaſon to doubt, but theſe conſiderations ſtuck cloſe to him, and gave a deep accent to every period, in his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> for he whoſe conſcience was ſo juſtly tender, as to be touched with a ſenſe of guilt when he had but offered violence to the utmoſt Garment of <hi>Saul,</hi> may well be ſuppoſed to be burthened now with that ſenſe, when he could not but know, that he had either been actually contributive to his fall, or at leaſt had ſuſpended that aſſiſtance, which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably might have preſerved him from it.</p>
            <p>From all which Conſiderations it will appear too clearly, what great cauſe <hi>David</hi> had to mourn on this ſad occaſion, and <hi>to lament with this la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over Saul, and over Jonathan his ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it ſeems he thought not himſelf alone concerned in this matter, but judged others alſo had cauſe to joyn in this Lamentation with him, and therefore accordingly he takes care and gives order that they ſhould.—<hi>Alſo he bad them teach the children of Judah the uſe of the Bow,</hi> which is the ſecond General I obſerved.</p>
            <p>In ſpeaking to which I ſhall be concerned to do theſe two things.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49568:11"/>1. To aſſure this Interpretation, and Senſe, that I have given of the words.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To account for the reaſonableneſs of the thing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then that this is the true Import and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine meaning of this Parentheſis, I can ſee no reaſon of moment to enduce me at all to doubt, but ſome very great ones to make me confident in believing.</p>
            <p>In order to the making of which to appear to you alſo, I muſt deſire you to conſider, that it was a common thing among the Jews, to affix ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Titles to their Songs, whether they were Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſtical or Hilaſterial, <hi>i e.</hi> whether they were deſigned to give praiſe for mercies, or whether they were intended to bewail guilt, and depricate puniſhments; for of both natures you ſhall meet with Songs in the holy Scriptures; and many of theſe with ſome particular names and titles affix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, of which in the Book of Pſalms we meet with many Inſtances, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Pſalms with ſuch Superſcriptions as theſe, to the chief Muſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian, <hi>Neginoth, Shoſhannim, Altaſhith, &amp;c.</hi> juſt as this, to the chief Muſician, <hi>Keſheth,</hi> or the Bow; the plain meaning of which is this, he bad the chief Muſicians, ſuch as <hi>Heman, Ethan,</hi> and <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duthun,</hi> to teach the common people to ſing this Song of Mourning for the death of <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this name of the Bow is given to it, with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49568:12"/> reſpect perhaps to the Philiſtine Archers, by whom this ſlaughter was made, as the precedent Chapter tells us; but more eſpecially with reſpect to the Bow of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> of which mention is made in it alſo, and by three Arrows ſhot out of which, by that trueſt of friends, <hi>David</hi> had notice of his danger, and warning given him to provide for his ſafety.—So that you ſee I make here the Bow to be the name of a Song, and not to denote that piece of Armature, that is expreſſed by that name, and ſo the learning the people the uſe of the Bow, is the learning them to ſing devoutly and Muſically this Song.</p>
            <p>And this Interpretation may be made good from theſe two Arguments.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The authority of ſome very conſiderable Verſions, and Expoſitors.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The unreaſonableneſs of the contrary Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By the authority of ſome very conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Tranſlations of this place: Such is that of the 72 Interpreters, and the Vulgar Latine, <hi>i. e.</hi> in all the Ancient Copies and Manuſcripts of it, as the Learned <hi>Gregory</hi> from his own Obſervation intimates in his Notes upon this place, from whom I am not aſhamed to acknowledge that I receive great help and direction in finding out this ſenſe; and ſuch alſo is that not to be contemned ancient Tranſlation of <hi>Tindal,</hi> in our own tongue.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49568:12"/>
            <p>And conſonant to this ſenſe is it underſtood by ſome very Learned Expoſitors, and would have been ſo by all, were it not that a fondneſs to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſome trifling Rabbies, have betraied them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the contrary.</p>
            <p>I do not deſire to be told (for I have hinted it my ſelf) that ſome of the Jewiſh Maſters under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand this place otherwiſe, I know it, and that they alſo have underſtood many others very ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculouſly, and have miſerably trifled, and ſaid many very unreaſonable things upon them.—And none more ſo, than what they have delivered with reſpect to Kings, and therefore ſomething re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative to our preſent matter, as perhaps you may hear more fully by and by.</p>
            <p>I do not ſpeak this to diſparage all Jewiſh Learning, I would have it encouraged by ſome, but not therefore idolized by others. I would not bring an Odium upon all the Rabbies, but I would not have their ſayings made Oracular, and the great Standard of Truth.</p>
            <p>For when God hath bleſſed us with a clear and full relation, and given us a key by which to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock more clearly all their myſteries, then ever they themſelves could. I do not know how to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count it a due veneration of that Revelation, to forſake it, to go and grope in Umbrages, and Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, and Types, and in fabulous Traditions and Legends, ſuch as moſt of their Books are ſtuffed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49568:13"/> much with, if not wholly compoſed of.</p>
            <p>Beſides experience hath atteſted the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous conſequences hereof; it hath been made e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident of late by a learned pen, how moſt of our Chriſtian errors have derived from an over valuation, and too great a fondneſs of Jewiſh do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines and cuſtoms; and truly I think it neither difficult, nor injurious, to give the ſame Origine to our late woful ſtate rebellions, and to ſhew the doctrines of the late Uſurpers, to be but the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripts of what the latter Jews do fabulouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of the power of their <hi>Sanhedrim</hi> over Kings.</p>
            <p>But I muſt beg pardon for this digreſſion and haſten to ſhow the unreaſonableneſs of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Expoſition, and that not only, 1. From the impropriety and inelegancy of the Speech, and the ſtrangeneſs of the <hi>Apoſtrophe,</hi> which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, in bringing in <hi>David</hi> beginning a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick lamentation, and then breaking off with an impertinent command, <hi>to teach the children of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah the uſe of the Bow.</hi>—But ſecondly and chiefly from the improbability of the thing; for it cannot reaſonably be thought, that the men of <hi>Judah</hi> were now to learn the uſe of the Bow, or ignorant of it; it was the common tactick pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice over all the Eaſt. And both <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> were excellent Archers themſelves. And the uſe and knowledge of the Bow was ſo very com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49568:13"/> that as Bread in the Hebrew Dialect is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly uſed to ſignifie all Food; ſo was the Bow, to denote all ſorts of Armature.</p>
            <p>This therefore now I take to be the granted ſenſe of theſe words, and truly cannot but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, if any one that hears it, do not preſently ſee the great conſonancy of it, and therefore from the reaſonableneſs of the ſenſe I proceed</p>
            <p n="2">2. To account for the equitableneſs of the thing. And certainly if there was reaſon for <hi>David</hi>'s lamenting the death of <hi>Saul,</hi> there was ſo alſo for the peoples joyning in conſort with him, and joyntly ſinging this ſad <hi>Expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For certainly, that man hath a ſtrange noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Superiority and Government, that thinks it not Inſtituted for the good and benefit of thoſe that live under it; but for the Grandeur and State of thoſe that exerciſe it. Vain men that judge by appearances and ſhadows, and look only on the outſides of things, are apt to ſtare at the Port of Kings, admire the rich Embroidery of their Robes, and thoſe ſparkling Diamonds that embelliſh their Crowns and Diadems.</p>
            <p>But wiſe men that ſee thoſe Thorns that are ſtuck in their Ermins, and thoſe great cares that their Crowns are lined withal, do very well know, and wiſely conſider, for whom theſe heavy Crowns are worn, and who they are that reap the benefit
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49568:14"/> of all this ſtate; and that is certainly the people, who therefore have great reaſon to condole their death, and lament their loſs, as being really their own.</p>
            <p>That Kings are great Bleſſings to their people, beſides the concurrent ſenſe of all Nations, might be made evident, from thoſe many great benfits, that accrue to their Subjects from their Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Government, without which, experience hath too often taught the World what a ſcene of things would preſently take place; for the ſight of which I would remit every one here, to the four laſt Chapters, in the Book of <hi>Judges;</hi> but that our own freſh, and yet bleeding experiences can tell more, and may juſtly ſuperſede all other no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tices of theſe things.</p>
            <p>The wiſe Greeks took care to tranſmit the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of theſe things, by thoſe very names, that Kings and Crowns were expreſſed by; for the Diadem is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, for the people, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Foundation that aſſures the peoples ſafety; and experience hath commonly atteſted the Wiſdom of the Word, in ſhewing how tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering the common ſafety is ſtill, when theſe are weakn'd.</p>
            <p>And almoſt all Nations have uſed appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of analogous ſignifications; for there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have they been called Shepherds, and Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians, and Fathers, and Gods, not only to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49568:14"/> the happineſs of enjoying them, but to expreſs the expoſed condition of theſe that want them.</p>
            <p>And it will add mightily to our ſenſe of this, to conſider that God himſelf hath uſed every one of theſe appellations; yea, even the higheſt of them, for Kings are commonly called <hi>Elohim</hi> in holy Scripture; and that not only becauſe they are Images of God's Power and Greatneſs, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are inſtruments of his goodneſs, and convey bleſſings to people ſo great, as juſtly to be entitled Divine.</p>
            <p>There is a place in the <hi>Pſalms</hi> (that I have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fen admired) and it is pertinent to our preſent matter: 'tis <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.7. <hi>Who ſtilleth the raging of the ſea, and the noiſe of his waves, and the mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> (or tumult in laſt tranſlation) <hi>of the people;</hi> as if the quieting of people, and preſerving them in order, were as argumentative of a Divinity, as the <hi>ſtilling the rage of the ſea,</hi> and that as both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeak the ſame Power in effecting of them, ſo the happy conſequences beſpeak the ſame goodneſs.</p>
            <p>And for theſe reaſons all Nations almoſt in the World have been ſtudious to pay the biggeſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours poſſible to their Kings; nay, have thought no mortal honours big enough for them, but have aſcribed them into the number of their gods, and at their death contended for their <hi>Apotheoſis.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49568:15"/> And this hath been one chief reaſon of idolatry, men thinking they could never enough honour their Princes, unleſs they turned idolators of them; which though it were an ill requital of God, by whom Kings Reign, and who confers ſuch bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings on men by their Miniſtry, yet it ſhews clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, what a great ſenſe they had of theſe benefits. And this hath been done not only amongſt the rude and barbarous Nations, but the moſt poliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and refined, even by the wiſe and grave Romans themſelves.</p>
            <p>Now theſe benefits of enjoying Kings, will be of uſe to give us the juſt meaſures of our danger, when we looſe them. I have ſeldom ſeen a tall Cedar fall, but the ſubjacent Plants have been bruiſed by it, and the whole Vicinage hath been ſhaken, and ſmarted under the effects of it. And if the welfare of the people do not always ſuffer, yet it is always greatly endangered, when theſe changes come.</p>
            <p>Beſides, God hath told us in his holy Word, that he often takes away Kings in his wrath, and that their death, as it is the Index of a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, ſo it is often the Prologue to many tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gical miſeries. And we ſhall find the like inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations commonly in his providence, for he ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom calls Kings to theſe Chambers of darkneſs, but himſelf hangs up Tapers to light them thither. Shaggy Comets uſually preceed the Funerals of
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49568:15"/> Kings, and as they are always ſtartling and amaſing Monitors, ſo they are almoſt always portentous, unleſs it be, when the prayers and tears, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of men interpoſe and obſtruct their malevolent influence.</p>
            <p>From all which things I ſuppoſe it ſufficiently intimated, what great reaſon there is, that the people ſhould lament the fall of their Kings, and <hi>the children of Judah be taught the uſe of the bow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But that's not all, it is not enough that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Generation do thus, but that ſucceeding ones alſo entertain the ſame ſenſe of theſe things: for ſo <hi>David</hi> here doth not only cauſe the preſent Generation to be <hi>taught the uſe of the bow:</hi> but he cauſeth it to be recorded alſo, for the notice and imitation of poſterity: <hi>behold it is written in the book of Jaſher:</hi> which</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is the third and laſt general Obſervable; in the underſtanding of which there can be no other difficulty, but only what we are to conceive this Book of <hi>Jaſher</hi> to be.</p>
            <p>That it is not the <hi>Bereſhith,</hi> the Book of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which the Jews call the Book of the juſt men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it relates the lives of <hi>Enoch</hi> and <hi>Noah,</hi> and <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> thoſe real juſt men, is ſo ridiculouſly plain, that it is confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on enough to repeat it: The Learned <hi>Maſius</hi> (I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member in his Notes upon <hi>Joſhua</hi> the 10. <hi>v.</hi> 13.
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49568:16"/> where there is alſo mention of this Book) only mentions this expoſition of ſome Rabbies, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to expoſe it, and let the World ſee, what pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful interpreters of Scripture they ſometimes are.</p>
            <p>And if we conſider how they make out this ſenſe, we ſhall ſee their trifling plainer: For this they ſay is written in that Book of the Juſt Ones, becauſe in the Bleſſing of <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Judah,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>his hand ſhould be</hi> (or his Bow, ſay they) <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the neck of his enemies:</hi> but (beſides the force of explaining Hand, by the Bow) the imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of it (if it were ſo) is very evident, for what relation is there between that Bleſſing, and this Curſe or Miſery? becauſe <hi>the bow of Judah ſhould prevail at laſt over his enemies, therefore Saul ſhall fall by the bow of the Philiſtins.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I ſtay too long upon ſuch triflings. <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> gives Learned Men a good ground to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret otherwiſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> of a Record that was depoſited and kept in the Temple, wherein ſeveral things of extraordinary moment were recorded for the notice of Poſterity.</p>
            <p>But that which will yet bring the matter near<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is the obſervation of Learned Men, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but metrical Compoſures, or Songs upon theſe extraordinary occaſions, were recorded herein. Some of the Ancient Jews have reckon'd up ten of theſe Songs, which it is probable were recorded in this Book before the time of <hi>Samuel.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:49568:16"/> Such was that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> at the Red Sea, and of <hi>Moſes</hi> before his death, that of <hi>Joſhua</hi> when the Sun ſtood ſtill, to give perfection to the overthrow of the Five Kings (which is expreſly ſaid herein to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded) and ſuch was that of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruch</hi> at the diſcomfiture of <hi>Siſera, &amp;c.</hi> it is not material whether we know them all or not.</p>
            <p>And to theſe doubtleſs in proceſs of time, were added others, and particularly this <hi>Epicedium,</hi> at the death of <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And then I had juſt reaſon to ſay, that this was not recorded only for the Notice but the Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and uſe alſo of Poſterity; for theſe Songs being thus recorded in a book kept only in the Temple, with directions how they were to be ſung (for that all learned men add too) is clear evidence that they were ordered at ſome ſtated times to be ſung and taken into the Common Service.</p>
            <p>That this book is now loſt, is no great won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; ſo is the Temple it ſelf, and ſo is the book of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Seer, and ſo is the book of the large Chronicles of the Kings of <hi>Judah,</hi> all which we know aſſuredly were written and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a conſiderable time among the Jews.</p>
            <p>So that I am now clear of this obſtruction, and the ſenſe is plain: this book of <hi>Jaſher</hi> was a book in which <hi>David</hi> recorded this Lamentation, with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49568:17"/> directions how it was to be ſung by Poſterity.</p>
            <p>And indeed this is not done without good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, for there are ſome great ends both of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Religion ſerved by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of Prudence, for there will be few me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods by which a deeper ſenſe of this great Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be impreſſed upon men, then by thus appointing the memory of it, to be attended with tears and a Solemn Mourning; for as all men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that men are not apt to mourn for nothing, ſo when they ſhall ſee wiſe and good men com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending things to be lamented, not only by the preſent Generation that feels them, but tranſmit the ſame ſad<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Memory of them to Poſterity, they muſt needs apprehend them not to be any common or trivial evils, but very great and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily concerning.</p>
            <p>And what excellent ends of Prudence and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment may be ſerved, by this only thing, <hi>i. e.</hi> begetting a through ſenſe in mens minds of the great miſery of looſing Kings, is eaſie for any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to obſerve.</p>
            <p>For this will moſt effectually endear the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of having Kings, and teach men highly to eſteem and value it; and he that doth thus, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not poſſibly be either diſobedient to their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, or trayterous againſt their Power and Perſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But then the ends of Religion in this, are
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49568:17"/> greater and more worthy of conſideration.</p>
            <p>For if we ſuppoſe this loſs of a King, barely as a great evil, without any reſpect to the peoples ſins that might have occaſioned it. Why then by commending it thus to the Lamentation of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity, men may learn both to be more fearful of ſuch an evil, and more awful of that divine wrath that doth inflict it, and more earneſt in their prayers, that they may never come into the ſad circumſtances of ſuffering it themſelves.</p>
            <p>But then if there be a great guilt occaſioning this evil (as Religion teacheth us ſtill to believe; for God afflicts not cauſleſly the ſons of men, and great judgments never proceed from God, but when great ſins in men call for them) Then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the ends of Religion in commending this Sorrow even to Poſterity, are great and import<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>For then this may ſerve as an excellent method to impreſs on men the greater dread of all ſuch ſins, and the ſtricter care to beware of them, for ſo good men ſet up marks where wracks have been made, to give notice that the next Paſſengers may avoid them. And ſo wiſe Religion, by enjoyning us to bewail the ſins of our Fore-fathers, doth excellently contrive for the rendring us more heedful of them.</p>
            <p>And yet it will be religious upon another great ſcore, <hi>i. e.</hi> in order to the eſcaping the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49568:18"/> due even to the poſterity of ſuch great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, for ſome ſins are of ſuch great guilt, and ſo extreamly facinorous, that they cannot be expia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the puniſhment of one only Generation, and in ſuch caſes, what is defective in the ſufferings of the Fathers, will be ſupplied in the ſufferings alſo of the Children after them, and the intayled curſe cannot be cut off, but by a ſignal ſorrow, and eminent repentance.</p>
            <p>But this Diſcourſe will perhaps be more ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable ſome Ages hence, when innocent Poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhall be told the ſtory of theſe things, and find our preſent moſt juſt Lamentation written in the Book of <hi>Jaſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And now I have done with the words in that firſt ſenſe I propoſed to ſpeak to them, and ſhall (in hopes of your patience) proceed to ſpeak to them ſomething in the ſecond; in which I ſhall not need to be ſo long as I have been in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</p>
            <p>For I no way queſtion, but your thoughts have already prevented much of what might be ſaid in the application of them to this day, and the ſad buſineſs of it.</p>
            <p>I ſhall therefore content my ſelf to tell you, that as we have the ſame thing to lament, that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> had in the Text; ſo all thoſe reaſons that ſtand ſtrong for the one, do ſo alſo for the other, and as they warrant this Lamentation of his, ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:49568:18"/> they will do the ſame thing for ours.</p>
            <p>For we have the untimely death of a King to lament, as well as he, and for the ſame reaſons too, ſo that ſo far we are equal.</p>
            <p>But there are two Circumſtances in which our caſe exceeds this mightily, and I name them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they both make our Lamentation more juſt and needful.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is the great difference between the perſons whoſe deaths are lamented.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond is the difference between the perſons, by whom their deaths were effected.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There was a great difference between the perſons: it is not to me a pleaſure to rake into the imperfections of any man, much leſs to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover a Fathers nakedneſs; it is no way becoming to reproach Kings, nor ſtrike them with the tongue, againſt whom a ſecret thought can hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be innocent. I do not intend to advance the Honour of our King upon the ruins of <hi>Saul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet as one Star differeth from another in glory, though all be lucid and glorious: ſo though there were many great excellencies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in <hi>Saul,</hi> yet it will be no diſhonour to his memory to ſay there were more in our King, and which is more, theſe were never ſullied by any one known vice, as they were in the other.</p>
            <p>I dare not venture at his character, nor go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to draw his Image before you, leſt it ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49568:19"/> ſuffer by ſo rude a hand, and leſt I ſhould Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane what I purpoſe to Honour; for he that praiſeth weakly and imperfectly, doth in truth diſhonour and diſparage.</p>
            <p>It ſhall therefore ſuffice me to tell you, and I have reaſon to believe it, that whatever was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to make him good as a Man, and honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable as a King, God had beſtowed upon him, in meaſures as great as humane imperfection is well capable here of.—And if one of his glorious Predeceſſors were Canonized, and is remembred to this day, under the Honourable Title of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, he doth juſtly deſerve the ſame Glory, and will ever be remembred by all good men, under the as glorious name, of the Holy Royal Martyr.</p>
            <p n="2">2 But ſecondly, there's a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Inſtruments, by which their deaths were effected. I do not know how to make any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon between them, unleſs it be in calling both <hi>Amalekites;</hi> and truly it will concern them to conſider, if they do not deſerve the name, and I pray God give them Grace to conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the curſe of <hi>Amaleck</hi> be not juſtly their portion.</p>
            <p>But here is the difference mighty and great: <hi>Saul</hi> fell by the hands of ſtrangers, from whom no better things could be expected, were it in their power to do it. But our Martyr fell by
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49568:19"/> the unnatural violence of his own Subjects, from whom all the World might expect better, by men who muſt firſt offer violence to themſelves, mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr their own conſciences, chaſe all remains of juſtice and compaſſion out of their own breaſts, before they could do this murther, and ceaſe wholly to be men, that they might commence Devils.</p>
            <p>For truly I do not know, how they can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect any better name, whom no tyes of Laws, no bands of Conſcience, no Obligations of ſolemn Oaths can hold, or reſtrain from the greateſt of wickedneſſes; If St. <hi>Peter</hi> were called Satan, for but out of a miſtaken expreſſion of Love, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to ſave his Maſter from running into danger; how much more juſtly muſt the curſed <hi>Iſcariot</hi> be called Devil, for betraying the ſame Maſter into that danger.</p>
            <p>But my buſineſs is not to upbraid nor aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate the guilts of theſe men; it is rather to bury them in a Sea of Tears, and beg us, by our Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Lamentation and Sorrow to caſt a Mantle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, that they may no more come into Gods remembrance.</p>
            <p>And to excite us all to the moſt paſſionate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, I ſhall beg the Patience of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Aſſembly, whilſt I endeavour to evinee the becomingneſs and neceſſity of it, from theſe four great Chriſtan Topicks.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:49568:20"/>1. The vindicating the Honour of our excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Religion from any Imputations of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary ro this fact.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Expiation of that guilt, that it may dye the Nation in, and prevailing with God for the full pardon of it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The prevention of thoſe puniſhments, that yet may be impending for it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The deeper impreſſing a care upon us all, to prevent with the greateſt concernedneſs all incidences into the like heinous ſin for the future.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the vindicating our Holy and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Religion from any imputations of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to this direful fact.</p>
            <p>And truly among all the ſad conſequences of this day, there are few or none that we ſhould be more concern'd for, than the diſhonour that ſeemed to be done to Religon by it, and none that we ſhould be more zealous for than to clear it of the ſame.</p>
            <p>I ſhall moſt readily grant, that were it any way chargeable with this fact, there needeed no other thing to be pleaded againſt it; this alone would bar all its pretences of being a Chriſtian for ever.</p>
            <p>For it is moſt certain, the Religion of the bleſſed Jeſus can be chargeable with no ſuch thing; nay, it is moſt obvious, that it takes all poſſible care to prevent them, that it ſecures ſubjection and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful obedience to Kings, by the ſtrongeſt tyes poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and makes it impoſſible for a true Chriſtian
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49568:20"/> to become Rebel upon any pretence whatſoever, as ſhould be ſhewed at large, did either the time allow, or my ſubject require the ſame of me.</p>
            <p>And there cannot be a greater miſchief done to it, than to give any juſt cauſe to ſuſpect the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary; it muſt then never expect Kings to be its nurſing Fathers more, but rather that they ſhould all combine to baniſh it out of the World now, as they did to prevent its coming into it at firſt, upon the ſame prejudice.</p>
            <p>But it was its honour, that it clear'd it ſelf ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all theſe unjuſt imputations, and commended it ſelf to Kings, and became dear to them, and was nurſed in their Royal Breaſts, and was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dopted into their Laws, as being the greateſt ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their Government, and of ſubjection to them.</p>
            <p>And what ever Religion doth contrary to this, is by that only Argument detected to be perfectly Antichriſtian; and truly were it my buſineſs to recriminate &amp; retort calumnies, I would take this occaſion to ſhew how truly unchriſtian all the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Factions amongſt us at this day, are in their Doctrines about theſe things. And I could eaſily make manifeſt, how very unſafe all of them make the conditions of Kings, and upon what weak and ſlippery grounds they found ſubjection to them.</p>
            <p>In this the moſt diſtant parties and ſections conſpire and accord perfectly. <hi>Gebal</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:49568:21"/> and <hi>Ameleck,</hi> and all. <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Geneva,</hi> the <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis</hi> and the <hi>Conclave, Munſter</hi> and <hi>Leiden,</hi> and what ever places have given denominations to any of theſe Factions.</p>
            <p>And I am not afraid to ſpeak it with ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, that if ſome men had power to act, and others durſt but ſpeak conſonantly to their prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, the late bloody Regicides would be Cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nized in <hi>England,</hi> and the Murtherous <hi>Jaques Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Ravilliack</hi>'s names would be writ in <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick</hi> in the <hi>Roman Calendar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my buſineſs is not to calumniate others, but to vindicate our ſelves. And it is the Honour of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that her Doctrines in this caſe are truly Chriſtian and Primitive, and that ever hitherto ſhe hath been untainted in her Loyalty, that ſhe hath had the ſame fate with her Kings, and not only fell with, but was perſecuted for her Loyalty to her Martyred Maſter.</p>
            <p>And it is certain when ſhe fails to be ſo, ſhe ceaſes to be, degenerates from her ſelf, and doth juſtly forfeit their protection.—But if God pleaſe to bleſs her, and Kings favour her till that time, there is little doubt but ſhe will remain till the great diſſolution. And as the pious and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious obſervation of this day may be one good means to prevail with God for this bleſſing; ſo it will be a ſtanding evidence of the injuſtice and malice of this immerited imputation.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:49568:21"/>2. For the expiation of the guilt of this great crime, and prevailing with God for a full pardon of it.</p>
            <p>The ſhedding innoceot blood is one of the greateſt of guilts, but the ſhedding the blood of good Kings is next to impardonable, when one man riſeth up againſt his brother and kills him, the Judge can judge him, and inflict a puniſhment e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual to the guilt, but when he turns Parricide, or Regicide, murthers his Father, and aſſaſſinates his Prince, his guilt becomes tranſcendent, and God only can inflict an equal puniſhment, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if any blood unjuſtly ſpilt cry loud and fix a great guilt; ſurely the blood of an Innocent King ſo ſpilt, muſt be ſuppoſed to cry louder and dye deeper.</p>
            <p>I find a Law amongſt the Jews, that when a man was ſlain, and the murtherer not known, the whole Land became reſponſible, and chargeable with the guilt, and therefore was to be purged by a General Sacrifice.</p>
            <p>But this comes far ſhort of our caſe, and makes ſuch a publick ſacrifice much more needful for us; for if that were due in caſe of any common murther, it is much more ſo in ours, where though ſome of the Murtherers be known, and have had the juſt reward of their crime, and it is to be hop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, God be in ſome meaſure appeaſed: Yet all are not known, and ſome that are, are yet (by a
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49568:22"/> mercy next to divine) ſpared; upon which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a continued Sacrifice will ſtill be needful to ſupply what is wanting towards the full at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement.</p>
            <p>This is certain, and a ſad truth, the Land may be ſaid to be defiled by this blood, and almoſt all ſorts of men more or leſs chargeable with it (as will appear if you will pleaſe to recollect what hath been before delivered) and therefore it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be leſs than abſolutely needful (unleſs we will ſtill lie in this guilt) to mourn publickly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord ſtill for it, and to interſperſe in our mourning (as the Church doth piouſly teach us) this Prayer: <hi>Heal our Land O Lord, and deliver it from blood guiltineſs O God, thou God of our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. For the prevention of thoſe Judgments that yet may be impending for this guilt.</p>
            <p>Where guilts are tranſcending, there what is wanting in a ſingle judgment towards expiation, muſt be expected to be ſupplied in many, and what cannot be ſufficiently puniſhed in a ſhort in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, will certainly be made up in the length of it.</p>
            <p>And truly we have juſt caſe to fear, God may proceed after the ſame meaſures with us, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count this Sin too great to be puniſhed in our Age.</p>
            <p>That this Land hath ſmarted under a <hi>ſeries</hi> of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49568:22"/> many heavy judgments ſince that black time, our yet bleeding experiences can too plainly tell us. And that ſome of theſe have carried on them ſuch clear ſignatures, as even point to this their great cauſe, the only calling them to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, will be clear evidence. And thoſe men that have uſed to be ſuch bold Interpreters of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidences, might do well to conſider.</p>
            <p>But yet whether our puniſhments have been in full proportions, and the voice of that blood be quite ſtilled, and God fully propitiated, he only knows, but we have juſt cauſe to be fearful, and therefore have as juſt cauſe yet to continue our religious Mournings, as we had to begin them, the next night that ſucceeded that Tragical day.</p>
            <p>I do not deſire to be counted a bold pryer into God's ſecrets in thus aſcribing thoſe judgments to this ſin. I bleſs God I have learned more Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an modeſty, and ſhall never (I hope) fall into that preſumption, which hath added to the guilt of thoſe mens ſins that were the Authors of this miſchief.</p>
            <p>Neither do I deſire to be told, that we have other ſins enough to deſerve theſe and worſer Judgements, I know it too well and could wiſh mine eyes fountains of tears to weep for them.</p>
            <p>But then I ſay, it ill becomes penitents in their Humiliations and Mournings, not to account for all known ſins, eſpecially if great and heinous.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49568:23"/> And it is a ſad ſign, when thoſe that would be accounted the only true Mourners in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and can be ſo exact in telling God their other crimes, ſhould never think fit to take this into their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions, and yet I am ſure they have moſt cauſe to do ſo.</p>
            <p>But becauſe they do not, I am ſure we ſhould, and make up by our repentances and mournings, what is wanting in theirs.</p>
            <p>But I have ſomething more to ſay to theſe men, I ſuppoſe they will not be brought to ſay they ſuffer'd for this ſin, before the Reſtauration. They were then indeed thoſe that made others ſuffer, and the ſufferings of the King being by them thought too little, they were made up, in heaping them upon all thoſe who either did, or could be pretended to have adhered to him—And ſince that time, it ſeems in theſe mens account all our ſufferings have been for other crimes. Therefore according to them, this ſin hath never been puniſhed at all yet, and perhaps they think never muſt. And yet they muſt either grant it to have been a great ſin, or elſe quit Humanity, and conſequently expect the puniſhment, or by Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance ſeek to avert it, or elſe they muſt quit their claim to Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid (as I doubt not but it will) that our moſt ſignal Judgements have been ſince the Reſtauration.</p>
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:49568:23"/>
            <p>I readily grant it, but yet think it a great advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage. Indeed till then, we were ſufficiently pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by theſe men, they made our loads heavy enough, and God was pleaſed in mercy not to make them heavier. And therefore ſince hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been the time, in which theſe Judgements could well be inflicted: Eſpecially if we conſider, that when the firſt means were uſed for the expiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this guilt, and Humiliations appointed to ſucceed them. Then the murmurings of theſe men began, and juſt like as after the execution upon <hi>Corah</hi> and his Complices, complaints were made, that the Lords people were ſlain, and men loſt the ſenſe of their former ſins, and began to contrive how to commit them again.</p>
            <p>So that it was then Gods time to ſtep in, and let an unthankful Nation feel his hand, and reckon with them for their former diſmal great miſcarria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: And therefore we may thank theſe mens mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings and unthankfulneſs, that this ſin was ſo ſignally, and yet is not ſufficiently puniſhed.</p>
            <p>And becauſe we have juſt cauſe to fear it is not, we have as juſt cauſe to continue our moſt paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate Humiliations and Tears, if thereby we may propitiate God, and prevail with him for a final ſuſpention of what is behind.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For the deeper impreſſing upon us all a great care to beware of all future incidences into the ſame Sins.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:49568:24"/>
            <p>This is the end, and this is the effect of all godly ſorrow, for men do not ſorrow in Gods account, when they ſin and ſorrow, and ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain; but when they ſo ſorrow, as to ſin no more.</p>
            <p>And to let this days Humiliation have this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect upon us, will render it truly Divine, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure Gods gracious acceptation and bleſſing.</p>
            <p>But without this, it will be but pageantry, and and add hypocriſie to our other guilts, and be but juſt like the Jews adorning the Sepulchres of the Prophets, which their Fathers had ſlain, when themſelves retain'd the ſame Principles, and were deſigning to murther the greateſt of all Prophets themſelves.</p>
            <p>And truly, if we lament the death of the Father, and yet retain the ſame rebellious principles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Son, our very lamentations are but mocking of God, aggravating our guilt, provoking his anger, and the more certainly aſſuring our own plagues. Then only will our tears attone this guilt, when they drown and take away thoſe evil luſts that did occaſion it.</p>
            <p>And here I cannot but expreſs my ſorrow, that there is any need to mention theſe things; and certainly it is a wounding reflexion, that all our great experiences ſhould be no better improved, and ſhould not have long ago ſuperſeded all need of any addreſſes to us of this Nature. A man might reaſonably think, that Engliſh men had
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49568:24"/> taſted too largely the bitter effects of rebellion, to hanker after it again, and experienc'd the great bleſſings of Loyalty and Subjection ſo fully, as to endear them to it, and fix them in it, beyond all poſſibility of being removed—And if it be not thus, it muſt needs be very ſtrange.</p>
            <p>But ſo that ſottiſh people the Jews grew quickly weary of the mild Government of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and in their hearts, (yea and words too) returned into <hi>Egypt,</hi> whoſe bondage they ſo very lately groaned under, and above all things wiſhed deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance from, and it will fix the ſame reproach of ſottiſhneſs, or ſomething worſe, upon thoſe men, who grow weary and impatient under the golden Scepter of a gracious King, and are fond of the Iron Rod of an imperious Uſurper. To all ſuch I muſt take liberty to ſay as <hi>Moſes</hi> did to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in much what a like a caſe, Do you thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite the Lord, O fooliſh people and unwiſe! Do you no better know your own mercies? Have you ſo poor a ſenſe of thoſe Miracles of kindneſs, that have bleſſed you with them? Do you wiſh with the murmuring Jews, that you had died in <hi>Egypt?</hi> Take heed of provoking God, you may have your wiſhes too ſoon.</p>
            <p>But I would fain hope, that I am needleſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vective againſt theſe things; and I am loath to have any thing to accuſe my Nation of. I would fain (in ſpight of the common proverb) ſuppoſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49568:25"/> them men, that are able to apprehend and judge truly of things that do ſo widely differ. And if ſo, it will ſoon appear a great truth, that Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is the intereſt as well as duty of Engliſh men, their being true to Monarchy is their happineſs, as well as their honour; paſt experiences have at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted how happy they have been under it, and late experiences have demonſtrated how impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it is for them to live under any other Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and then the inference from both theſe, one would think were eaſie.</p>
            <p>And I cannot but congratulate the happineſs of the Engliſh Genius in this, for it is the juſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and prelation of Monarchy, that its ſafety conſiſts in the wealth and happineſs of its Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, when few inſtances can be given of any Common Wealths that have flouriſhed much lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, than while neceſſity and poverty were their ligatures and cements; and it is the good hap of a people to be ſo naturally inclined to that, which is much their intereſt, and their felicity.</p>
            <p>But I am called this day to ſpeak before this Great City, I would therefore crave leave, to conclude with a ſhort addreſs to it.</p>
            <p>I do not come to doubt the Loyalty of it, no, but to congratulate it rather, and I take the ſo religious obſervation of this day to be a ſtanding evidence of it. And I can no way queſtion but ſuch wiſe men, that have ſignalized themſelves
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49568:25"/> by their prudent Government of this City, and preſerving Order in it to ſuch meaſures, that no ſuch City in <hi>Europe</hi> can boaſt the like, and have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived juſt marks of honor for it from a King, that can never fail to reward Merit, do very well un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand their own duty, and know how to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mean themſelves accordingly and will never ſully the glory of theſe actions, and the honour gotten by them, by any thing unworthy of either. It is juſtly to be hoped, that as the late fire hath truly refined this City, it riſing up in a ſplendor much greater than was before, ſo that it hath melted down all <hi>faeces</hi> and dregs of undutifulneſs that were formerly in the hearts of any of its In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants. And that as Juſtice ſeems written on your Gates, ſo Lonalty will be the Imbelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of your Palaces. And I am the more confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in my hopes of theſe things, becauſe all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering men will clearly ſee theſe three great things to depend upon it, and be ſecured by it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The honour and ſafety of the King.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The honour and welfare of this City.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The welfare and quietneſs of the whole Kingdom, all theſe (next to God's bleſſing) will be ſecured by the Loyalty of this Capital City.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The honour and ſafety of the King; for as the honour of a King is in the multitude of his Subjects, ſo his ſafety conſiſts in the love and affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and loyalty of theſe Subjects, and the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49568:26"/> the number of Subjects that are embodied, is, the more conducive to his ſafety is the love of them, ſince they can always be more ready as well as able to yield him aſſiſtance, and to ſtrike de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpair into any that would attempt againſt him.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The honour and welfare of this City it ſelf, he that will ſearch into the cauſes of the decay or ruine of Royal Cities, will ſoon find their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting from their King to be one great one. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not multiply inſtances (becauſe I have not time) of this. I ſhall only beg you to call to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance an inſtance in our next Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> it will be hard for any man without tears to read the miſery of that City not very long ago, but the cauſe is obvious, it was being ſeparated from their King, by the Faction of the Houſe of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> and by the bewitching charms of a Holy League; if you will recollect your own miſeries in the late times (which I have ſeen ſome of you weep for) you will be able to aſcribe it to the ſame cauſe, effected alſo by the ſame means, <hi>viz.</hi> the enchant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sorcery of a Solemn Covenant.</p>
            <p>Honourable and Beloved, this is a great truth, the ſafety of the King depends upon the welfare of this City, and the welfare of this City depends upon the ſafety of the King. And if men would look into the truth of things, they would ſoon perceive that their intereſts are complicated, and indeed the ſame. The ſafety of all Bodies (next
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49568:26"/> ever to God's bleſſing) conſiſts in the firm coheſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its parts.</p>
            <p>And it is true in experience as well as ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And who ever will trace either the ruine of the King, or ſubſequent miſery of this City to their firſt Origins, will ſoon find the Artifice of ſome men in ſeparating them from each other, effected both.</p>
            <p>And you may ſee the ſame things plainly ſtill; for theſe men that deſign now the ſame things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, do purſue them ſtill by the ſame method, it is here that they firſt ſpread their Nets, and place their Engins, and their diſappointment here, will cauſe deſpair and unſuccesfulneſs ever to attend their miſ-chievous devices.</p>
            <p>And therefore my aſſurance that I ſpeak to wiſe men, gives me aſſurance alſo of their great care ſtill to diſappoint theſe men. For as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Surely in vain the Net is ſpread in the ſight of any Bird:</hi> So ſay I, if we permit the ſame men, by the ſame methods, to trapan us again into the ſame crimes, and make us ſerve to the ſame evil purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes again; we then make our ruine our own guilt, as well as our miſery, and muſt periſh as unpiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed fools for ever. But God (I hope) hath reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us to better purpoſes, and will give us grace to purſue wiſer Counſels. A few days paſt have given good hopes that the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Engliſh Nation is recovering it ſelf, and your hearty com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliance with thoſe great and (I hope) wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49568:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> will be mighty contributive in order to giving effect to theſe hopes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But the effects of your Loyalty will not be confined in ſo narrow a room, but will be extended to the benefit alſo of all the Kingdom. It is you that ſtamp the practice of all the Nation, by your carriage they take their meaſures, and make your Actions their Preſidents. So that you'll not only ſave your ſelves by your ſignal Loyalty, but you'll be influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ential alſo, in ſaving the many thouſands of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The ſeeds of Loyalty ſown in this plot of ground, will quickly ſpring up into a Tree whoſe branches will extend to the diſtant ſhores, which together with the Royal Cedar, will make a Shadow, under which your ſelves, and all the Nation may ſit ſafely, and ſing praiſes to God chearfully, and be happy in the Contemplation of your great Bliſs.</p>
            <p>And now I have done, but that methinks I ſee ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the countenances of this Audience, which incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rageth me not only to beg that you would, but prophecy alſo that you will, exerciſe your ſelves in theſe Tacticks, ſing this Lamentation with ſuch hearty accents of pious ſorrow, as may reach even to the Throne of God, and be accepted by him, and prevail with him for pardon of the guilt of the death of the Father, and a Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to deſcend upon the head of the Son, and that God will graciouſly pleaſe to add thoſe years to the life of this, which he was pleaſed to ſuffer to be ſubſtracted from the life of the other.</p>
            <p>That we will all learn to ſhoot skilfully in this Bow, ſuch Arrows as ſhall be ſharp in the experience, as well as midſt of the Kings and our Enemies.</p>
            <p>That as Engliſh Archers have been renown'd for their Chivalry in earth, ſo they may ever be bleſſed for their Loyalty, in Heaven. That all our names may be recorded in the Book of <hi>Jaſher,</hi> and be found written in that Book of the Upright and Juſt Ones at the laſt day, and our portions of Bliſs be eternal with theirs in Heaven for ever more. Which God of his infinite Mercy grant for Chriſt Jeſus his ſake. To whom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
